<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[C]ertayn and tru good nues, fro[m] the syege of the isle Malta wyth the goodly vyctorie, wyche the Christenmen, by the fauour of God, have ther latlye obtayned, agaynst the Turks, before the forteres of Saint Elmo / translat owt of Frenche yn to Englysh.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1565</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17213.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2227</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23162667</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23162667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26326</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1799:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[C]ertayn and tru good nues, fro[m] the syege of the isle Malta wyth the goodly vyctorie, wyche the Christenmen, by the fauour of God, have ther latlye obtayned, agaynst the Turks, before the forteres of Saint Elmo / translat owt of Frenche yn to Englysh.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[G. Manilius],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Gaunt :</pubPlace>
                  <date>27 of August M. ccccc. Lxv [27 Aug. 1565]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Malta --  History --  Siege, 1565.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26326:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26326:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ERTAYN AND tru good nues, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſyege <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Iſle Malta, wyth the goodly vyctorie, wyche the Chriſtenmen, by the fauour of God, have ther latlye obtayned, agaynſt the Turks, before the forteres of ſaint Elmo.</p>
            <p>Tranſlat owt of Frenche yn to Englyſh.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>And nuli prented yn Gaunt, the 27. of Auguſt.</p>
            <p>M.ccccc.Lxv.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26326:2"/>
            <head>The copie of a letter writen, by the ryght honoroble lorde, brother iohn valet, great maſter ond Comander of the Rodes, now Malta, to the ryght noble &amp; worthke Capitayn, don Garcia of Toledo Capitayn general to the kyng of ſpayn. Contayning the late nues laſt com from Malta, wyth the horrible &amp; pyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aſſautes made by the Turks apon the ſayd fortreſsis, and the fayer victori, wych the Chriſtians had before ſaynt Elmo, the xv. &amp; xvj. day of Iune laſt paſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YNS I ſent vnto your honor the vertuus knyght ſaluage, I wrat twyes, &amp; ſent the letters to Gozzo, God grant they may ſurely paſſ, and afterward we ſent fourth alyght boot wyth owers, cauled a fregat, wych making all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to goo &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were browght to ſuch neceſiti, being abowt .ij. leagues owt yn the ſea, that they were fayn to take flight to ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelf, for aſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as they were chaſed by thenimies, &amp; they caſt theyr lettres yn to the ſea, &amp; ſo retournyng reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered agayn the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Malta, by the grace of God. After the ſiege of Marzo Sirocco was remoued, &amp; I forſeyng to be ryght neceſſari to aduertiſe your honor, that the hauen ys not year ſo neare enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyth thenimie, I cauſed to be browght from the land a brigantin, or ſmal ſhyp, to Marzo ſcala, bycauſe the ſyege of owr enimies lyeth on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſyde, I hoope the ſame ſhall come wythowt
<pb facs="tcp:26326:2"/>any ſtop (wyche God grant) a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that to aduertyſe your honor that the .xv. day of Iune, toward eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, the hwole armye or ſyege wyth all theyr ſhyps paſſed by here, that they were eaſili percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of owrs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hauen, ſo that the nyght hyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dered vs nothyhg, for the great noyſe wych the ſhyps &amp; galleis made, wyche were al dyſarmed, &amp; yll apoynted, hauing left their hole, &amp; good ſhyps at Marzo muſcheto, &amp; one part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at ſaynct Giorgis. Whye the ſyege of Marzo Muſche to ys rayſed, the cauſe thereof ys lack of freſh wat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and yt may be for the great feare they haue of the armye of your lordſhyp, for as we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de they be aduertyſed how there are yn a reddines at Meſsina 150. galleis &amp; other ſhyps, therfor they dare not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo fer as ſaynt Pawles ſtayers, but lye as neare to their armie (wych ys a lond) as they poſsible may, neuertheles albeyt that this place lyeth ſo nye, year ys yt not ſo ſure, yf they were yn haſt, they myght hardli co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyr ſhyps, as thowgh they were ferder of, on the ſide of Marzo Sirocco ys not one man to be ſene, for they haue left yt vp, &amp; ſet fyar on the howſis of ſaynt Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins, &amp; ſaynt Ihons, now they begon from the ſayd Marzo toward theyr ſyege, wych ys alway before ſaynt Elmo, we ſe playnli that almyghti God purpoſeth to defend the ſayd place of ſaynt Elmo, for aſmuche as yeaſterday in the morning owr me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſyſted more by miracle, then other wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, one aſſault during .iiij. howrs lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, wyche theni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="tcp:26326:3"/>dyd make yn dyuers placis, ſpeciali at a bryd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that was bwylt by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wyth the maſts &amp; decks of .iiij. galeis, on the ſyde of Marzo muſcheto, wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che aſſault they made .iiij. tymes, &amp; ſo furiuſli that at euerie tyme they browght freſh men, &amp; at eueri tyme were repulſt, &amp; bet back wyth great loſſ of theyr men, and not wythout loſſ of owrs, for of owr ſyde remayned ded two hundred, and. 150. hurt and Capitan mirande was ſtayn wych was great gryef vnto vs, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of turks were ſlayne abowt 2000. and as many hurt, and they were left the moſt part yn the dyches of ſaynt Elmo, wyth this victori owr men be ſo encorraged &amp; made har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, that I truſt to keape thys place u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyl the comi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of your lordſhyps exelence, not wythſtanding owr enimies be muche refreſhed, &amp; more fyers &amp; deſperat, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before, as I haue not ſene the lyke, for they haue ſhot wythin .xv. dayes .xiij. M ſhot of artilarie, neuertheles yf I may flynd ſoccours (as I hoop to do) by meanes of owr galleis I dowbt not a whyt, but to keape thys place, for the ſaff gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding of the wych, I haue almoſt ſpent all that I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, goods &amp; men, and we are reſolued &amp; vtterli determined apo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this poynt, to dye toguyther, hoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping and looking affter ayd, &amp; ſoccours fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your exelence. Conſidering &amp; ſeyng yn what dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gier we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yn, thorowgh long tarians a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, we beſeke your exele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, not to fayle to gyue vs ſom aſyſtance, at leſt wyth ſom nomber of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant men, wyche is eaſie to be don, by that good
<pb facs="tcp:26326:3"/>meanes I haue certified you, ſeying the ſyege ys retyred from Marzo ſyrocco they may la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yn the ſame ſyde cauled pietra nigra, all owr comfort &amp; hoope, next God, ys yn your exelence, to the wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; ſubmyt my ſelf hwolye, prayng the God almyghti for good auenture, &amp; proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti. From Malta the xviij. day of Iune 1565.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Subſcribed <hi>By me I. Vallet.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="newsbook">
            <head>Relation made by ORLANDO MAGRO pilot to the chyff galley of the great maſter coma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Rhodes, now Malta the wyche aryued at Meſsina the .xxvij. day of Iune 1565. And ſayth:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW THAT HE PARTED from Malta the ſonday .xvij. day of the month, about half an owr after ſon, and .iiij. companions wyth hym wyth aſmal fregat of iiij. ewers, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:26326:4"/>letters of the great maſter of Malta to don Garcia, &amp; ſayth that the turks hauyng ſhot agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the fortres of ſaynt Elmo. xviij dayes toguyther, wyth .xxiiij. peacis of great artillari &amp; aſſaulted yt ſondrye tymes, at the fyrſtaſault got the vttmoſt fortres wythout the dychis, named ſaynt Ruelino the ſecond tyme they went wyth 2000. men and ladders prepared to enter, and laſt, wych was fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day .xv. day of this month, they hauing made a brydge wyth the maſts &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cks of iiij galleis, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming yn to the trenchis, ryght ouer againſt where they had made the barterie, hoping &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king by thys meane, eaſli to enter, but they fownd them ſelf deceyned, for they wythyn defended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo valiantli, and the brydge wych the Turks had made, burnt wyth gon powlder &amp; artificiall fyer, and beat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yn ſuche ſort that ther remayned ded. 800. Turks, and 600. hurt, and owr men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke .ij. enſygnes one of the wyche was, of the gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral Capitan by lande named Prali, and thother was of Dragut, yn thys aſſault were mounted vp. 30. Turks an hye ouer the bulwark and they of the caſtel of ſaynt Angelo ſhot to ſtryk thes. 30 turks, and ſtroke ded eyght of owr own men, and after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward charged, and ſhot agayn, &amp; ſtroke thes. 30. Turks lykwiſe ded all ſauyng one, among the wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ther wer vj. of the howſ of the rayes, &amp; one was capitan general of the Rhodes, whoſe name was Portuch hali, &amp; the other dragut wyche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned onlye alyue.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26326:4"/>
            <p>This aſſault dured fyue howres toguyther, ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che that the Turks were forced to retyar back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ther wyll wyth great loſſ of theyt men. In this aſault dyed of owrs abowt. 200. and 150. hurt &amp; wonded, and of the Turks wer ſtayn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt. 2000. &amp;. 2000 hurt, of wych the more part were left wythin the trenchis &amp; dychis of ſaynt Elmo. Item, that Dragut apon ſonday the .xvij. day of the month ſet fyar yn the bulwark, or baſtilion, wych they had made. Yn the market place of Marzo mulcheto, wher they had .iiij. great peacis of artilati. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that after the laſt aſault, the moſt part of the ſyege, retorned by nyght to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the galleis, and are remayned a land onli a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowt 3000. Turks, to gard the artillari, and they ſhot now wyth no mo then ſyx piecis, and that they haue ſhot yn all abowt. 13000. ſtroks or ſhot. Item, that .ij. dayes before their laſt aſſault their ſyege was retyered from Marzo Sirocco, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brent the fortres wych they had mad ther, &amp; retyered toward the valey of ſaynt Paul, where thys pylot leaft them at hys departyng thence. Item, that certayn Chriſtiens taken by the Turks and eſcaped again affirme, that they ſayd yn the Turks armie, that don Garcia had a hundred and fyuetie ſhyps and galeys to guyther to recounter wyth them, and that the Turks had great feare, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d therfor they went the moſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nyght to theyr ſhyps Item, that the great maſter writeth how thei had fownd a quyckſpryng of freſhe wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:26326:5"/>wythin the town named Burgo, wych wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thowght as a miracle.</p>
            <p>Item the maſter of the poſtes of Meſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ina wrat that the galley of portuch hali wyche was ſlayn yn the aſſault was bowged and ſonck by owr ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilarie Item that the baſſa takyng the muſter of hys ſowdyowrs and nauie, fownd fower galleys lackyng, of hys nomber.</p>
            <p>Item, we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by other letters, that when owr enymies came to offer to let thys brydge wych they had made vearie artificiali owr men wyche were wythin were yn great dowbt &amp; feare, yn ſo muche that they were ons determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to render the place, but thorowgh good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration and the grace of God, &amp; by the hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of one valiant knyght hauing a two handed ſwerd yn hys hand, ſaying that he wold dye for the Criſtian fayth, gave to all the reſt ſuche cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, that they obtayned at laſt the victori. Item that the great maſter was veari ſorrowful for the death of Capitayn mirande.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
